\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

CSCI-345/780 Coding Guidelines

Introduction

All code that you submit for this course must be easy for me to read! That means it must be laid out on the page so I can see the structure of the code easily, don't have to scroll horizontally to read anything, and that there are comments to help me find the significant parts of the code in each file.

It also means that your comments should be "just enough, not too much." That is, you do not need to document the obvious and should assume that your reader knows the Handel-C language. Nor do you need to demonstrate to me that you know what you are doing. I will be able to tell that by how clean your code is and how well it runs.

Think of documentation as what professionals do when they write code so that others can maintain it after they have moved on, and you will have the right idea for dealing with this issue for this course.

Guidelines

Here are some rules for how to document your code. They are not hard and fast, but they should give you some ideas of how to achieve the goals outlined above.

Set your editor to substitute spaces for tab characters. In DK, you do this from Tools -> Options -> Tabs. Doing this makes sure that your code indentation will look right no matter what program settings I use when I read it.
No line of code, including comments, may extend beyond column 80. This is not always practical, but it is a good general rule for preventing horizontal scrolling. I have a program that tells me exactly how many tab characters and long lines there are in your source files, so watch out!
Put the name of each source file in a comment in the first line of the file. Sure, the file name is normally in a title bar somewhere, but putting it at the beginning of a file helps the reader keep track of what he or she is looking at.
Put a comment block at the beginning of each source file telling what the program does, who the author(s) is(are), and when the program was written. This is a matter of professionalism. But it helps readers navigate through projects with multiple modules more easily, so it serves a very practical purpose too.
Put a comment block before each function, macro proc definition, and endless loop. Make sure this comment block stands out on the page. For example, put a horizontal line below the name of the function or macro proc name, such as the following: Sample comment block for a function or macro proc

    //  main()
    //  -------------------------------------------------------------
    /*
     *    Description of what the function does goes here.
     */
      void main(void) ...
      

This is another case of helping the reader navigate through the source code efficiently.
Be sure there is at least one space between comment leaders and the text that follows. (“Comment leaders” are // for single line comments, or /* or * for comment blocks.) Format the comments so they are easy to read and document the logical structure of the code.
Put spaces around operators to make the code easier to read. “x += 3;” is easier to read than “x+=3;”
Be sure all code compiles and builds with no errors or warnings for both Debug and EDIF configurations. The only exceptions are the Pal macro expansion warnings (“possible infinite expansion”) that do not indicate a problem.
Be sure the Xilinx tools report no problems, such as an inability to meet timing constraints

Vickery Home - CS-345/780 Home - XHTML - CSS
Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

Configuring DK

Introduction

There are several steps involved in setting up Celoxica’s DK GUI for doing projects in the lab. Some of them need to be done just once, while others need to be done for each project -- but many of the per-project settings can be copied over from other projects, saving some overhead.

The purpose of this web page is to run through the settings you will need to manage, hopefully in a form so they will be easy to refer back to as necessary.

Directory and Workspace Setup

When we set up your account we put a directory named My Projects under your My Documents directory. You will need to create one DK workspace for the semester, and you will be doing several projects during the semester. You will tell DK to create the workspace in your My Projects directory, and then will create each project there.

Start DK, and click the File->New menu, and click on the Workspace tab. Set the Location to your My Documents folder (you can browse to it using the “...” button), and type My Projects as the Workspace name. If you were to exit DK now, you would see that DK creates two files in your My Projects directory: My Projects.hw and My Projects.pref The .hw file where DK keeps information about the workspace, basically just a text list of the projects in the workspace. The other file is where it will record the preferences, some of which you will need to adjust.

Before making the preference changes you need, create your first project. Bring up the New panel again, and this time, click on the Project tab. On the left side, click on Library (the fifth icon down), and in the Project Name text box, put DelayProcs. I suggest not putting spaces in project names to make things easier later. Be sure the “Add to current workspace” radio button is checked. If it is grayed out, you need to go back and make sure the workspace you set up above is open.

Now create a source code file for your DelayProcs project. Open the New panel again, and this time select Source File, select “Handel-C Source File,” and enter msec_delay as the File Name. When you click OK, an editor window will open up: type a comment line with the file name at the beginning:

// msec_delay.hcc

Save your source code file (Control-S) and exit DK. Verify that the .hp and .pref files mentioned above are in your My Projects directory, and that there is now a subdirectory named DelayProcs. In the DelayProcs directory there should be two files: DelayProcs.hp holds the housekeeping information DK needs for the project, and msec_delay.hcc is your source code file. Like the .hw file, .hp files are just text files that you could look at with a program editor if you wanted to.

Be sure your workspace and first project are set up as described here before proceeding! If they are not, delete everything under your My Projects directory and repeat the above steps.

Start DK and open your workspace again.

Go to Build->Configurations and Remove all the build configurations for this project except “Generic.”

Add the code for macro proc msecDelay() to msec_delay.hcc. Be sure the Active Build Configuration at the top of the screen says “Generic” rather than “Debug” (or anything else) and build the project. There should be no warnings or errors. If you look at your project directory (DelayProcs) you should see a subdirectory named Generic, and inside that you should see an object file named msec_delay.hco and a library file named DelayProcs.hcl.

Set Default Preferences

Click on Tools->Options to bring up a big panels for setting options. Once you set these up, you won’t have to change them again.

On the Tabs tab, set the tab size to either 2 (the value I personally like) or 4 (another popular value), but make sure it is not anything larger than 4 to avoid code that gets so wide it can’t be read without horizontal scrolling.
Click the “Insert spaces” radio button: tab characters in your code lead to mixed up indendation (or even none at all) depending how particular programs or printers interpret tab characters. What your code looks like matters in this course!.
On the Format tab, change the font for the Output Window category to a fixed-width font, such as Monaco.
On the Directories tab, select “Show directories for Include files,” and add your DelayProcs directory to the list. You will be putting a header file here shortly. Select “Show directories for Library files” and add the pathname to the Generic you created for your library file above.

Create and Configure a Simple Project

To complete the setup process, you will need to configure your first application. We will use an application that turns a LED on and off once a second as an example.

Add a header file to DelayProcs

First, construct a header file that guarantees that the definitions of the macro procs in your DelayProcs library agree with your use of these procedures in your applications. To do this, add the following Handel-C header file to your DelayProcs project:

// delayProcs.hch #ifndef __DELAY_PROCS_HCH__ #define __DELAY_PROCS_HCH__ extern macro proc msecDelay(clock_rate, msec); #endif

The preprocessor directives are a conventional mechanism for making sure that cpp doesn’t accidentally get put into an endless loop inserting one header file that includes another one that includes the first one again. (Current versions of cpp check for this and won’t actually loop, but the convention of testing for and defining a preprocessor symbol based on the file name remains.)

Add this directive to your msec_delay.hcc and make sure you can re-build the library without warnings or errors:

#include <delayProcs.hch>

By enclosing the header file name in angle brackets (< >) instead of quotes, you are telling the preprocessor to look for it in one of its “standard places,” namely the directory you added to the Tools->Options->Directories tab above.

Add a project to the workspace.

Create a new project called Flash_A_LED. Be sure DK adds it to your workspace. Note that the name follows the convention of not having any spaces in the project name.

You will configure the project for two target platforms: Simulation (Debug) and FPGA implementation (EDIF). To avoid accidentally using some other configuration, remove all but these two configurations from the project using the Build->Configurations menu item.

There are several settings you need to set up for each project. The good news is that once you set them up for one project, you can copy many of them over to new projects somewhat mindlessly. You get to the settings panel from the Project->Settings menu item.

There is a table of configuration settings for various platforms for you to refer to for the values you will need to enter.

Enter all the values for the Debug and EDIF settings for this project.

Write the code and build the two configuration.

Add a Handel-C source file named flash_a_led.hcc to the project, and enter the following code:

// flash_a_led.hcc /* Turns a LED on and off once per second. */ #include <stdlib.hch> #include <pal_master.hch> #include <delay_procs.hch> // main() // ------------------------------------------------------------------ /* * Turns a LED on, waits half a second, turns it off, and waits * another half a second. Repeats forever. */ void main(void) { while (1) { PalLEDWrite(PalLEDCT(0), 1); msecDelay(PAL_ACTUAL_CLOCK_RATE, 500); PalLEDWrite(PalLEDCT(0), 0); msecDelay(PAL_ACTUAL_CLOCK_RATE, 500); } }

Note that including the same delay_procs.hch header here as you used in msec_delay.hcc makes the compiler check that you use the same number of parameters when invoking the macro as you used when you defined it. However, because msecDelay() is a macro rather than a function, there is no checking of the parameter types.

Use the “Active Build Configuration” box at the top of the DK window to select the Debug configuration, and build the simulation using the F7 key or by clicking on the blue toolbar button that is supposed to look like a building (but doesn’t really). Do the same for the EDIF configuration. Be sure there are no errors, and be sure the EDIF process goes all the way through the “Bitstream generation complete” stage successfully.

Test both project configurations.

With Debug selected as the active configuration, press F5 to start simulation. Two windows should come up: a black Command Line window from Windows and a “Pal Virtual Console Window.” There should be a flashing LED on the Pal Virtual Console. The exact rate at which the LED flashes will depend on the PC’s clock speed and the target clock rate you chose in the project settings. To stop the simulation you can either close the Windows Command Line window or click the DK toolbar button with a red X in it.

To test the FPGA configuration, launch one of the File Transfer Utility programs provided by Celoxica: FTU2 for the RC200E (parallel port), or FTU3 for the RC10 or RC300 (USB port). Make sure the FTU detects the kit you have attached to the PC, browse to and select the bit file, flash_a_led.bit in your Flash_A_LED/EDIF directory, and then click the Configure button or just double-click on the file name in the FTU’s list to download the bitfile to the FPGA. A LED should flash exactly once per second.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

How To Divide By 3

Introduction

Doing arithmetic on an FPGA is different from using a CPU. There is no single Arithmetic Logic Unit that receives operands from a fixed bank of registers and to which results are returned. There are various ways of mapping an algorithm onto the logic cells of an FPGA, but the general model is that separate hardware is generated for each expression to be evaluated. In Handel-C, the circuit to implement a function can be reused in different parts of a design. But consider code like this:

a = b + c; c = d + e;

In a CPU, a single ALU would be used to perform both additions, but on the FPGA, two separate adders will be generated to perform them.

There are two tradeoffs that make the FPGA approach attractive compared to the general-purpose ALU approach used in a CPU:

The FPGA circuits are tailored to the calculations involved. If the variables in the example above are just 3 bits wide, then the adders will each consist of just 3 full adders each. No circuits are wasted providing a capability to add 32-bit operands when they are’t needed, for example.
There are significant speed advantages possible using the FPGA approach. For example, if an FPGA can evaluate a complex expression like a + b *c + d in one clock cycle (using two adders and a multiplier), whereas the same calculation would require a sequence of three instructions (assuming the operands are in registers) to evaluate using a single ALU.

One goal of an FPGA design, then, is to eliminate as much unnecessary calculation as possible, thereby reducing the complexity of the circuitry the compiler generates. The complexity of an adder or subtracter grows linearly with the widths of the operands, but the complexity of a parallel multiplier grows with the square of the widths of the operands. Division is much more complex than multiplication. For example, to multiply a 20-bit number by the constant value 3 requires 19 logic elements on a Quartus Cyclone FPGA, but dividing a 20-bit number by 3 requires 141 logic elements. (“Logic elements” remains an undefined term at this point.) The question, then, is whether division by a small constant can be implemented more efficiently. The algorithm developed below divides a 20-bit number by three using 40 logic elements in the Quartus/Cyclone environment.

Note that the technique here is probably not worth pursuing if your design involves just a small number of divide operations; as long as the design fits in the FPGA and meets any timing constraints that might exist, there is no need to go any further.

A complication involving division is that the result usually has a fractional component, which may need to be rounded. For the present discussion, we will assume you want to compute the average of three 20-bit signed integers to produce a signed quotient that has been rounded to the nearest integer value, also being represented in 20 bits.

Fixed-Point Numbers

Think of an integer as a number with a binary point at the right end. The bits in the integer have weights of … 22, 21, 20. But you can think of that same integer as having a fractional component without affecting the circuitry needed to do addition or subtraction. For example, you could position the binary point three positions over from the right end, giving bit weights of … 22, 21, 20, 2-1, 2-2, 2-3.

Adding the integers 15 and -1 to produce 14 (0011112 + 1111112 = 0011102 is identical to adding the fixed-point numbers 1.875 and -0.125 to produce +1.75 (001.1112 + 111.1112 = 001.1102: the only difference is in how we humans interpret the location of the binary point.

In this example, the smallest fraction that can be represented is 0.125 (000.0012), so we say this fixed point notation has a precision of 0.125 or, equivalently, of 3 fraction bits.

As long as all operands are represented using the same number of fraction bits (have the same precision), their binary points will line up, and integer arithmetic will work just fine for doing calculations. However, if the binary points don’t automatically line up and/or you are working with a set of operands that sometimes need more fraction bits and sometimes need more integer bits to represent their values you would need to work with floating-point numbers. Floating-point numbers also let you work with a larger range of values for a given number of bits by using scale factors and approximations instead of exact representations of extremely large and extremely small values. The problem with floating-point numbers is that it takes a lot of circuitry do arithmetic using them. Fortunately, fixed-point notation is a totally satisfactory way to work with fractions for many FPGA-based applications, including the problem at hand: taking the average of three numbers.

Multiply Instead of Dividing

We already saw that multiplication requires less circuitry than division. One way to simplify things is to multiply by the reciprocal of the divisor instead of actually dividing. When the divisor is a constant, its reciprocal can be pre-computed. Of course the reciprocal of an integer will be a fraction. For example, to divide by 3, we can multiply by 1/3 (0.010101…2). Note that this particular value is a repeating fraction in both decimal (0.3333…) and binary. Two issues have to be dealt with: precision and rounding.

In this case, two bits of precision is the same as dividing by 4, because the first two bits of the multiplier are 0.012. The fraction would be equal to the rightmost two bits of the dividend. Three bits of precision would make the multiplier 0.0102, which is numerically equivalent to the 2-bit multiplier. So you need to go to four bits to increase the actual precision.

Assume we want to take the average of 3 integers and that the result will also be an integer. This will require four bits of precision to differentiate among the possible remainders (0, 1, or 2) reliably. So our multiplier will be 0.01012, (0.312510.) Six bits of precision would give a decimal value of 0.328125 for the multiplier, which should not improve the accuracy of the rounded integer result.

To round to the nearest integer, we can add 0.10002 (0.510) to the product before dropping the fraction bits to get the rounded integer quotient.

Add Instead of Multiplying

With four bits of precision, multiplying by 1/3 is the same as multiplying by ¼ (0.01002), multiplying by 1/16 (0.00012), and adding the two products together. Here is an example of dividing the decimal number 8 by 3 and rounding the result:

001000.0000 8.0 000010.0000 2.0 = 8.0 / 4 + 000000.1000 0.5 = 8.0 / 16 = 000010.1000 2.5 = 8 * 0.3125 + 000000.1000 0.5 (rounding factor) = 000011.0000 3.0 (rounded quotient) 000011 3 (integer answer)

In summary, to compute the average of three 20-bit numbers:

Sign-extend each of the three numbers to 22 bits and sum them. The extra two bits guarantee that the full sum will not overflow.
Place an imaginary binary point four places in from the right of the 22-bit sum. Without actually doing anything to the bits, this is the same as multiplying the sum by 1/16. To be used later, this copy of the sum must be sign-extended to 24 bits.
Sign-extend the sum to 24 bits and shift it left two bit positions. Again assuming an imaginary binary point four places in from the right, this value is the sum multiplied by ¼.
Add the above two sums to produce a 24-bit sum with 4 fraction bits.
Add the rounding factor and drop the fraction bits.

All of the above can be done in one clock cycle, but here is a Handel-C code snippet that shows the algorithm being done in 5 separate clocks:

sum = adjs(x,22) + adjs(y,22) + adjs(z,22); one_sixteenth = adjs(sum, 24); one_quarter = (adjs(sum, 24) << 2); avg_with_fraction = one_quarter + one_sixteenth; average = (avg_with_fraction + 0b01000) \\ 4;

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .

\n"); } else { header("Content-type: text/html; charset=utf-8"); } ?>

Hardware Lab Syllabus

Reading Material

There is no textbook for this course. Rather, your reading and study assignments come from three sources:

Reference Manuals
There are several manuals available online that you will need to consult as you work on the laboratory assignments for the course.
Laboratory Assignments
There will be links to the laboratory assignments for the course on this semester’s course schedule as they become available.
Web Modules
There are some Java programs that are referenced from the laboratory assignments. Some illustrate concepts, and some provide tools to help you do the assignments.

Course Structure

The syllabus for the course consists of a series of laboratory assignments designed to provide you with a basic mastery of hardware design using Field Programmable Logic Arrays (FPGAs). The structure varies from semester to semester, but there are typically five assignments, with each assignment normally consisting of more than one project. Assignment grades are based on coding style, coding efficiency, and documentation. The assignments will make up approximately 20% of your course grade. You are expected to work with a partner on the assignments, and you are encouraged to seek help from and to give help to other people in the course when working on the assignments. However, each team is to submit its own version of each assignment.

At the beginning of the semester and occasionally later in the semester as well, there will be lectures. Normally, however, you will be spending your class time in the laboratory in Room A-227. The software in the lab requires a license to run, but you can access the lab computers, as well as some additional ones that are in Room A-205, from off campus provided you have a broadband Internet connection. In addition, you can get a key to the lab from the department office when it is open, or from the campus main gate on weekends. You need to work in the lab itself in order to test your projects on the laboratory kits.

There will be a midterm and a final exam, which will be based on material covered in lectures and on both the principles and the techniques learned by doing the laboratory assignments. The exams will count 40% of your course grade each.

Vickery Home -  XHTML -  CSS

Last updated .